- Hi. Good morning everybody.
Welcome. How are you doing?
Did you go to the morning session?
How are you feeling after that author?
Huh?
- Depressed. - Depressed?
Well, you have to get a sense of, you know,
the rah-rah and all the good
with some of the "Let's think about it."
So don't be too depressed,
but you have to have a balance with everything.
So we wanted to make sure that, you know,
we're supposed to be thought-provokers
and we're supposed to be thinkers.
And so whatever we teach our students,
we're teaching ourselves to.
I wanna welcome everybody here today
for day two of the Future Summit,
and the start of our breakout sessions.
I'm here with these lovely people,
which I'll introduce in just a moment.
And my name is Anu Khanna,
I'm with Foothill-De Anza Community College District
and also with the Digital Center.
And this is Ryan Matteson
with the Cal Poly Digital Transformation Hub.
We have our student Christopher King,
and they'll introduce themselves more as we start the panel.
Sharon Liang from Cal Poly,
Devani (indistinct) from Cal Poly,
River Covey, who's also one of our students,
talk about himself in just a second
when we get to them.
And Nick Osterbur from AWS and Cal Poly.
Oh. (laughs)
(audience applauding)
- I love this crowd.
- We'll give multiple round.
We all need encouragement, right?
So we are here today to talk about
what we call challenge accepted.
I had the opportunity earlier this summer to join
all these wonderful people at Cal Poly
for a week long summer intensive AI summer camp
that was really set up for students
to be able to gain some real life skills,
and problem solving,
and finding ways in which to create some AI driven solutions
to problems that higher ed institutions,
the community colleges and CSUs submitted
to the Digital Transformation hub to say,
hey, we have a pain point, we have a problem.
Can you help us?
And so we are here to talk about what that was like
and what our students learned, and how we might scale
and replicate that going forward.
It was a fantastic experience,
and we wanna make sure that you can see
what's possible when we teach our students skills,
let them be creatively challenged,
give them some technical skills
and what comes together and what happens.
So with that,
I'm going to pass it on to my panel
as I ask them questions
to tell you the story of what happened at Summer Camp.
Nick, I'm gonna start with you.
What's the history behind this AI summer camp
and how did it come to be and how was AWS involved?
- Yeah, thank you for that.
- Oh, is it working?
Here, have this one. - Okay.
Test.
Got it. Okay. Thank you.
Okay, so before I go totally into that answer,
I want to kind of maybe queue up like how we got here,
the program that I work in,
and then what the Cal Poly DxHub is.
So I work for Amazon Web Services,
I'm a digital innovation expert.
I came from the Cal Poly side some seven plus years ago
when the Digital Transformation Hub was first established.
And I work in a broader program at AWS
called the Cloud Innovation Center.
There's a number of cloud innovation centers.
There's one at ASU,
there's one now at the University of Pittsburgh,
and then a sister institute
up in British Columbia that focuses on healthcare.
And our program is really about how can we empower students
and work with public sector organizations
to create open source solutions
that ideally are gonna start to solve problems at scale.
As you can imagine, we're very AI focused these days,
that isn't, you know,
our focus is really about being, you know,
rabid trying to solve the business
or the mission problem
that a public sector institution brings to us.
And then working with students to pull that off.
So with that, I wanna maybe ask Ryan to explain like,
what is the Cal Poly Digital Transformation Hub
from the university view?
And then maybe we can start to unpack
kind of how that summer camp idea came around.
- Yeah, yeah.
So why do we have a DxHub at Cal Poly?
There's many good things that come from it,
but for part of us for, hello, hello.
Hello, hello, hello.
Good. Great. Thank you.
At Cal Poly,
we are about building new and innovative things,
and we also had a time about seven, eight years ago
when we did not have capacity
to do new innovative things.
And so the DxHub for Cal Poly is a pilot light,
a kernel of innovation.
We are a small and lightweight and very focused team.
We are three full-time employees to AWS
and one Cal Poly, myself.
And then what really is the magic is bringing together
the right problems
from our passionate public sector customers
and a team of students.
And as they speak, you'll kind of understand more
what their role has been.
So at the DxHub every day we are all working side by side.
This is the kind of partnership
where we are all rolling up our sleeves
and working on real things.
And for us,
the summer camp was out of a need to scale.
We were always looking for ways
to take what we were doing and share it.
We are very open source focused.
Everything we build, we share the source code.
We would like as many organizations as possible
to get value from our work.
And so, as we worked more and more with AI
over the last couple years,
we saw dramatic in opportunity,
we can open up the playing field
so everybody can build solutions.
It's not just for computer science folks anymore.
And that has been a fantastic process for us
to discover and unpack.
And so for us, what summer camp came out of is,
take what we do every day in our day jobs
and make it available to community college students
in a week long intensive in-person program.
- And so it kind of started back in February.
My team was having an offsite
and a planning meeting in San Luis Obispo.
And my manager and the leader of our program
kind of threw out this challenge,
like how can we do a broader scale
of what we're doing all day every day
at the Kick Program, right?
And at the DxHub.
And so I don't know how the lightning went off, but it did.
And I was like, what about like a summer camp
where we basically try to compress what we do at the DxHub
and then offer that to as many students
as we possibly can
in a very intensive,
kind of in real life human to human sort of format.
I also teach in the master's in business program,
specifically generative AI
to kind of like quasi technical students as well.
And so, you know, it was relatively easy
to take what we do all day every day at the DxHub
along with the curriculum from that class,
and then start to kind of package that up and then down
and compress that into an event like the summer camp.
And so we, you know, we originally did this for the CSU,
so it started with the CSU specifically
and the CSU,
I don't know if folks may or may not know that
the CSU and the governor's office
kind of did this big announcement
about really kind of fine tuning student experiences
to really harness AI
to be that kinda workforce to the future.
And so this idea really kind of, you know,
intentionally strategically mapped to that as well.
And, you know, to be like totally candid,
like we were making all of this up as we went along.
So started as an idea in February,
started holding our first, you know,
got the, you know, the resource committed.
Got started doing kind
of first formal planning meetings in March
and then just kind of just making it up
as we went effectively.
So apologies for being a little sloppy,
'cause it totally was, it was agile
and it was almost like an innovation experiment
in its own right. - Yeah.
And if we could like pull that thread a little more.
This is how we work.
And so we talk about a culture of innovation
and I've, previously, I was deputy CIO,
I was information security officer,
so I know rigorous frameworks and processes,
but we're about doing responsible things,
but doing it creatively, quickly
and focusing just on the pieces
that are really valuable to our customers.
And so I would say,
this is how we do all of our projects by design
and then we mature them over time.
We do an experiment and we see what works.
- Yeah, yeah.
And this was an experiment to be totally clear.
It seems to be a very successful experiment,
which we're excited about.
So we'll see what that looks like moving forward.
So we did the CSU thing
and basically it was a,
the start of it was,
let's mock up some, you know, submission forms
and a flyer both for the student participants
as well as for these kind of real world challenge sponsors.
We've got some in in the crowd here.
Thank you for showing up
and thank you for sponsoring real world problems.
So back to that theme,
like at the DxHub, in the Kick Program,
it's all about students doing the learn by doing thing
and actually tackling like real world problems
that are meaningful and impactful if solved,
just to be totally clear.
So we did this kind of joint campaign.
We had folks with lots of relationships,
kind of reaching out
to all the different lines of business throughout the CSU
to find those problems.
We also did,
and then on kind of similarly on the participant side
and thank you for all the folks that helped there.
We also did some pretty hardcore grassroots effort,
Devani and Sharon, thank you so much for your effort.
I'm like, hey, can you create a campaign
where we're like grassroots emailing every student club
and every student officer on, you know,
at all these different campuses?
And I think that worked out quite well.
And then we just started seeing the student interest
just start rolling in
and we ended up with close to 900 in about three weeks.
So the demand signal was like, so clearly there.
We vibe coded this fun little dashboard
and we were seeing these numbers come in in real time.
We're like, well, somebody just went out
and activated Fresno,
look at all these numbers come in, right?
Somebody just activated Pomona,
look at all these numbers come in.
And then at that point it was kinda like,
well there's probably one moment in time.
There's like this window, this passing window.
At least this is my gut instinct
where this demand is so real,
right here, right now.
And, you know, it baked, it was a good assumption.
I think that if it was that popular
and in demand for the CSU is probably equally,
if not more popular for the community college system.
And you know, we had some internal discussions,
like we've gotta extend this opportunity
to the community college system
and the name of, you know, equitable access
and all those good things by design.
And so, you know, one thing led to another,
we had some great data to back up,
this kind of secondary commitment
and now all of a sudden we're doing two summer camps
back to back weeks, which was a lot.
And then I started pushing for K12
and I think Ryan was about to-
- Had enough. - Yeah. Yeah.
I had to pump the brakes.
So anyway, within about three weeks we had,
I think 1300-ish community college applications.
Still very kind of grassroots
and thanks again to some of the top cover
and getting the word out,
kind of to chancellors and digital center level as well.
And so then now we had this big problem like,
how do we figure out how we're gonna execute on this
and, you know, give the right folks
the opportunity to show up.
And I dunno if you want to lean into that one at all.
- Well, I mean we have a very repeatable recipe
for how we do things day to day
and month to month in our day jobs.
And, but there's a big challenge in how do we scale that,
and compress it and keep the most important elements
and also, you know, honor the principles,
which are rule number one, it needs to be fun.
It's not competitive, it's not team A, versus team B,
everybody is supporting each other.
People need to learn a lot still.
It's learning outcomes that we care about
and ultimately solving a real problem
that's a special part of the recipe.
So those three things and how do we compress that all down?
And so we know how to do these things,
but we had to adjust and tune a lot every single day
leading up to that camp.
- And I'll just jump. Whoops.
I'll just, can you hear me?
Yeah, I'll just use my teacher voice.
I'll just jump in and say,
it really was grassroots in a very quick kind of,
let's get to, you know,
let's get these students in.
To get to 1300 applicants,
there was a need and there was an interest
and it was, we just emailed the contacts that we had.
We emailed, you know, VPIs at different colleges
because we said, can you talk to your instructors
and see if anybody will just send this out
and say, are your students interested?
Because we didn't wanna just target computer science majors,
it wasn't just for certain types of majors,
it was for any student who might be interested in that.
And so to get very quickly 1300 plus applications,
yeah, there's an interest
and students wanted to do this.
And so I think that's amazing to do that
just when you're trying to do it grassroots
and by, you know, who do you know
and let's see if we can push this out
and get people to apply.
- Thank you.
And so we laid out some basic tenets.
Ryan was kind of starting to allude to them like,
we gotta have fun, rule number one, gotta have fun.
It's gotta be in real life, like human to human.
There's no better time than right now in my opinion at least
to be like all down in the trenches, you know,
kind of trauma bonding if you will.
I don't know if that happened for you all, but. (laughs)
- [Ryan] I have never felt more optimistic
this year in those two weeks. Yeah.
- Yeah. It's gotta be an authentic experience
that everybody cares about, right?
And wants to take away
and start to like plant the seeds
for building and growing a broader longer term community.
So like community, community, community, community.
That was a big part of the theme.
And I hope you'll kind of like met some people
that you're gonna know for the rest of your life.
Sounds like maybe that's starting to happen a little bit,
which is exciting.
And you know,
and all those other great things we talk about,
learn by doing real world problems.
Teamwork, we really kind of harped a lot on
the durable kind of soft skills,
not just the hardcore technical
and, you know, the equity by design.
Like, I'm kind of still ratioing,
I think like half of the students that showed up
were probably computer science or software.
I think a quarter,
I'm just guessing a quarter was probably in the STEM realm
and then a quarter was just totally non-technical entirely.
So bringing all of that together, you know, in one room
for a full week was really interesting and exciting.
- [Anu] And how many people did you bring
into the room that week?
- What did we end up with? 80. - 80.
- About 80 - Plus. Yeah.
- Yeah. So I think- - A hundred students
were from that 1300 applications.
It was called down to a hundred invitations were made.
- Yeah. - And there was
an intentional effort to
try to get a wide range of majors and experiences,
and you know, whether they,
if they indicated they were first year, or second year,
or third year community college students.
And we also tried to get a mix across
the community colleges,
districts and colleges.
So we had, with the a hundred invitations,
we had 43 colleges represented.
- And I think the,
my observation was the age range in the community college
was 18 to 55 or 60 maybe,
some folks with just really, really interesting
and diverse backgrounds.
So hopefully that was a part of the fun that happened there.
So to answer a second part of the question
and then I'll roll into Mike here.
The AWS side, the Cal Poly side,
we put students up on campus housing at Poly Canyon Village.
I think the walks were a little too far
and burdensome every single day,
but I don't know,
it's probably also good for your mental health.
And so funding for that, the resource around that,
the resource around meals, the programming,
obviously kind of the curriculum,
the mentors like maul we've got here showed up.
And then our DxHub mentors.
So our DxHub team was just like full all in.
It's knocked us out for like a month by the way.
So it was very resource intensive
and kind of mapping this back to the original challenge
that my manager had thrown out there,
like how do we do this at a broader scale?
You know, I think we started with,
we've got resource to conduct this experiment,
let's see how it can be done right.
Let's pull those lessons learned
and then let's figure out
how to kind of distribute that resource
burden sharing a little bit.
And so lots to talk about I think in the future
about where this could go, but okay.
Does that cover?
- Yeah, I think so. - Okay.
- [Anu] Does anybody have any questions right now
about the program
as otherwise I'm gonna transition to the students
and let's hear about their experiences.
We'll try to leave time at the end for questions too.
Okay, Christopher, I'm gonna start with you.
What happened when they got to summer camp
is they were put into teams
and they were given challenge statements,
which were some of the collected challenges
and problems that we collected
from a lot of the community college leaders that we knew.
And we had put out requests and said,
does your institution have a pain point?
Is there a problem that might be benefited from
with some kind of AI driven solution?
If so, give us a challenge statement
and we're gonna have the students work on that.
So the students were put into teams
and then it was their charge to work on that solution.
Starting, you know, starting on Monday afternoon,
I guess you got together Monday,
you were given some technical skills and get going
and Friday they were gonna pitch and present their solution.
And so Christopher, I'm gonna start with you.
What challenge did your team work on
and can you tell us about your project
and what you tried to solve and how you did that?
- Yeah, so what we worked on was a project assigned
by the Foothill-De Anza Community College District.
And basically what our application
or platform aimed to do was to connect students
with learning differences or disabilities
with tutors that are suitable
to teach based on the needs of that student.
And it's something new, right?
And we harness the power of AI.
Basically how the experience goes is that,
a student will fill in an application form,
the AI will go through every single field
that the student with a learning difference entered
and it will then match it to a tutor.
And it's really sick because, sorry.
Yeah, we, it's-
- You don't need to apologize.
- Oh yeah, it's- - Your generation.
- Yeah, no, it's really sick
because we use this concept called
retrieval-augmented generation.
So basically it's not just the AI working,
it's retrieving context from a vast, like, knowledge base.
And AWS helped us with this through workshops
and yeah, that's basically what our platform did.
- [Anu] Well one of the things we talked about why.
- Yeah.
- [Anu] One of the things we talked about
when you were in your team was
I had the opportunity to go spend the week with them
and be a mentor and walk around
and work with some of the teams and talk to them.
One of the things we talked about was,
okay, you have a problem which is,
these students have learning disabilities, okay?
- Right. - They need to be matched up
and they're not always going to be able
to be meeting with a virtual tutor
because a tutor might not be available.
What if they're studying in the middle of the night.
- Exactly. - But a regular chatbot
may not be able to accommodate
based on their learning difference or learning disability.
- Right. - How did you address that?
- Yeah, so that's a really great question.
Basically, so right, if you schedule a tutor,
it's gonna take some time for them to come back to you
and, you know, help you with your homework
or your exam, right?
So what we did was we integrated a chatbot
into an app, our platform,
where while the student is waiting
for their next appointment with their tutor,
you get to chat with a chatbot
and that chatbot has context
of what the student needs are.
So for example, if you're, you know, you have ADHD
or you have some sort of reading impairment,
it'll try to adjust through those context
and give an appropriate response
that's tailored to the student's needs.
And we also integrated this in our UI.
So for example, you know, if you're dyslexic,
we implemented a feature where you click a button
and there's a dyslexic friendly view
where the fonts get weighted down at the bottom.
And you know what's really cool about this project is that,
most of it was powered by AI.
So those like UI changes,
those are mostly guided by AI.
- [Anu] What was the most surprising thing
that you discovered
while you were working on this project and with your team?
- Yeah, so the most surprising thing
that I learned through this project was that,
building the MVP and building production level projects
are different.
So when we are in the summer camp,
we're mostly doing this thing called vibe coding,
where the code is basically, you know, assisted,
as AI assists us to write code.
'Cause again, not all people in the team are technical
and you know, what's really cool about
the time we're in is that
you could just code in natural language,
like English and that comes with side effects.
Like it can be hard for,
like this type of code to be in production.
So I guess that's surprising that, you know,
if you're building an MVP, sure it works,
but if you put it in production it might not work, right?
There's like multiple edge cases that
you don't know what's gonna happen.
And I guess a recommendation I could give is that,
if you're integrating AI tools
and educational infrastructure,
there's a lot of studies that needs to be done
in order to make sure everything goes smoothly
and the platform doesn't break.
'Cause there's a lot of things that can go wrong with AI,
like, you know, like there's railroad features,
rail guards, and there's also like ethical concerns too.
So yeah, that's my insight.
- Can I ask a quick question?
Who was your team's mentor?
- Oh yeah, so our team's mentor is Sharon.
She's like the most helpful person ever. Well, yeah.
And she helped us like through like 12:00 AM,
like I was like, you you need to get a raise after this.
(all laughing)
- She did. - She got a raise. Oh nice.
- That's good because she, like,
she was working till 12:00 AM with us and like
we were really thankful. - We gonna ask her.
- [Anu] Sharon, so I'll turn it to you for a moment then.
Since you mentored this team,
what was it like to be a mentor
and what are some of the dynamics that you saw
with the team members and especially
because it was such a diverse group in the team,
what did you observe?
- Yeah, so yeah,
I had the pleasure mentoring Christopher and his team
and within that team it consisted of,
like so many diverse backgrounds.
We had Christopher who was like younger,
who just started off at CC
and then we had some members
who were coming back to CC
to learn more about computer science.
We had a juror, someone who was a PM, a product manager
and then we also had someone who was more business focused.
So it was really inspiring to see
all these different perspectives come together,
work together to build a solution
in such a short amount of time
and seeing these different perspectives work together
to build a more inclusive solution
because you have, you know,
people who are more technical like Christopher
who is like who has a CS background
and then you have other people who are more business focused
or even like Lasha who was a juror
trying to learn more about AI.
So it was really inspiring to see all of that come together.
- [Anu] Great, thank you.
River, I'll come to you.
What project did your team work on
and what was your experience like,
and how did you solve this problem
that was given in your challenge statement?
- Yeah, of course. So my name's River.
I was at Saddleback Community College in Orange County.
I recently transferred to San Jose State University,
still studying civil engineering.
And the project that we were working on
was a shipping project.
We received procurement data of different ways
that Cal Poly slow ships things in and out.
And our goal was to use AI
to optimize their shipping methods.
The way we were able to do that was really cool
to be able to be involved with,
because AWS gave us access to tools that
I wouldn't have access to
unless I was involved in a camp like that
because some of them have credits,
some of them cost money
and so we didn't have to think about that stuff,
which was awesome.
And so I worked alongside
and in some capacities as like a project manager
because as a civil engineer
with computer science background,
I felt I could relate to like people
with business backgrounds, people with,
I think there was a engineering systems
or something like that, background,
communication background.
And so I was able to give them specific goals
that they could work on
and then I was able to use AI
as Christopher mentioned,
vibe coding allowed those less technical people
to provide code
and it allowed us more technical folk like the CS students
and engineering students to integrate
those less technical deliverables
with like the more technical backend.
And that wouldn't have been possible without AI
and those specific AWS tools that we had access to.
And the way I solved the problem with my team
was essentially building a chatbot
where you could interact with the shipping data.
We also gave access to,
I called it like Expedia for shipping
because we had an API call which pretty much reached out
to like FedEx, UPS, postal service
and got their prices
and like the price per dimension
for shipping something to somewhere.
And so instead of having to go to like FedEx
and type all that in,
and then go to UPS and type all that in,
you're able to go to like the freight lease shipping hub,
which my project developed
and you could see all the different,
like shipping price options,
then you can interact with them with a chatbot
to be like, oh, I want it to come as fast as possible,
or I want it to be as cheap as possible,
and it would actually be able to interact with you.
And then we're also able to use machine learning tools
to go through that procurement data
and analyze where potential savings could be made.
One of the ways we found that is that,
we found they had shipped
from one supplier six separate times.
And so if they had just shipped one time,
they could have saved X amount of money.
And so I think we projected 15 to 25,000
in potential shipping savings
which could go back into like student funding
and different groups and organizations.
And so all this was possible with AWS and AI tools
that really like, increased our efficiency
and increased our like potential.
Like the potential that we had
compared to if we didn't have access
to these tools is remarkable.
- [Anu] When your team was trying to decide their solution,
did cost savings or cost savings
and kind of capacity for workflow, did that?
what kind of conversations did you have around that
to come, you know?
- Yeah, definitely as far as when building the project
or for like, the like, deliverable
because when developing a project
do you want to understand like,
oh, are my API calls gonna be costing money every time,
I like call them.
But then you also wanna be considering like,
how can this project help the business save money?
And so I think thinking about it from both ends,
like who's asking for it
and who's giving it out in both ends,
you can like apply saving methods and stuff like that.
- [Anu] Yeah, I asked that because we could see
as we were walking around that it wasn't always,
the conversations weren't always
around the technical skills,
but there were lots of conversations about
what does it mean, where's the value,
who's being helped and how are they being helped?
And I think that's a lot of the conversations
that we've been having since yesterday here,
that the technology is a technology
but what are we actually using it for?
How are we applying that
and where is that actually helping us as humans
and how are we part of that?
And so it was really interesting to see
the students engaging in those conversations.
You know, there were flip charts all around the room
and you know, they're brainstorming and talking
and so they're doing some of the work that we are doing too.
And in these conversations they just
did in an intensive week long experience.
Devani you are also a mentor for one of the teams,
so I'll ask you what was it like to be a mentor
and what dynamics did you observe
and how did you help the teams move forward?
- Yeah, so I was also one of the mentors for the team
and honestly it was such a rewarding experience for me
because I got to share everything that I have learned
working as a software developer
for the DxHub with my team and all the students.
And I saw everyone grow so much in terms,
not only in terms of technical skills,
but also as a person through the week.
So that was really inspiring for me.
And like it was mentioned before,
we had so many students come in from different backgrounds
with different technical levels, different skills,
and I was able to work with teams
to like bring out the best in them
and really use the skillset
that they provided
to build a real tangible solution in just a week.
So honestly working with them,
I also really got a unique experience as a student
because usually I'm the one
who is working on these projects,
but this time I got to be on the other side of the,
like on the other side helping students,
guiding them through their projects.
So I think I also learned so much as a developer myself
and yeah, it was an amazing experience overall.
- [Anu] Ryan or Nick, what was some takeaways
and surprises in terms of what you observed
as you were helping mentors
and students work on these projects?
- Okay, I'll start.
So first off, I think the chief feedback that we got
from the DxHub team after it was all over was,
you didn't tell us
what this was actually gonna be like at all.
(all laughing)
And so I think is that, okay?
And so like I think what we saw was,
I would argue that a lot of our team members
are introverts by nature maybe, right?
And then all of a sudden this script flip happened
and you don't know until you know,
until you experience
what it's like to all of a sudden,
'cause like Ryan and I are,
and our colleague Darren are always,
are constantly like, mentoring you, all right?
And now all of a sudden you have to jump in that role.
And I think it was like, it even totally surprised me,
like when that second week was over
you could just like hear the big gasp of relief.
And so I think that was probably the most interesting thing
and I'm super looking forward to hearing like,
did that experience, you know,
help you all as mentors and teachers.
'Cause all of a sudden you guys were doing breakouts, right?
And you were like literally teaching
a specific concept to all
and let alone just like hunkering down
with a specific team
and just doing, you know, the mentorship piece.
So I think that was probably the biggest surprise for me.
I just don't think I would have understood
really what that was gonna mean.
- Yeah. And I think also if we reflect back
at the start of the week, Christopher,
like Monday morning we start handing teams projects
and they're very clear about the time they have.
And some of these projects have very large
ill-defined scopes by design,
we chose them very carefully.
And we had a strong sense it would be possible
to do some good work on them.
I was surprised by how much work was done.
It was remarkable.
You used that word before
of between the vibe coding,
but really between the connectivity
of the members of the team.
I think that's what allowed it to happen.
And of course it's a high intensity supported environment,
but there is a dynamic on being on a team, it's hard.
It takes a lot of extra effort
and to do that all within a week.
And so what I guess surprised me most was,
the community college students
within five minutes you were connecting with each other.
You had maybe less in common in terms of your skills,
your experience, your location,
but you made those bridges immediately.
And so, I mean Cal State University employee,
we had a great first week.
The second week I think was even better
in ways we tuned some things,
but also a lot of it was just that connectivity
and that willingness to reach out
from all of the participants and to support each other,
to explore together
and to honor rule number one of having fun.
- That's true. - And it also just felt real,
like, it was not sanitized.
It felt like a real community was coming together
in real time, somewhat spontaneously.
- [Anu] Chancellor Christian yesterday talked about
the vision 2030 and what we hope for, you know,
the two million students that we have
in the community college system
and how we can train and retrain and upskill our students.
And again, emphasize it's not just about technical skills,
but also the durable skills.
And so you touched on that a little bit
in terms of the teamwork,
but I'll ask the students, you know,
Christopher or River, you can both take a turn at this.
As the week progressed,
you were definitely applying some of the technical skills
that you were learning
and you know, there were breakout sessions in between
of how do you vibe code and how do you,
what were some of the other ones or other sessions?
- RAG. - RAG, yeah.
I was trying to learn and keep up too,
but it was really hard.
But, and you know, we talked about how to present and pitch.
As the week started to get to the point of,
we have to pitch on Friday,
what was that like in terms of what you did in your teams
and how did you prepare for that?
Because that's beyond technical skills,
now you're getting into some of your durable skills
like problem solving, presentation,
communication, teamwork.
So can you talk about a little bit about your experience
and how you all came together to pitch at the end?
You wanna start River?
- Yeah, I'd love to start.
I think one of the special things about this program
was the fact that we were on campus for five days,
like 24 hours a day just hanging out,
talking about AI with other students
that can resonate
as far as being community college students.
And yeah, one of like the best parts about that,
is like I have so many friends,
I have four friends at SJSU now.
I have a group chat of like five people.
I talked to them today,
I got like exciting news and I sent it to them
and we all encourage each other and stuff.
And so just developing those relationships with the,
like friends from San Francisco, to San Diego,
and Long Beach,
and everywhere has been really cool.
And then just like being able to,
sorry, I kind of lost track of what I was saying.
Do you wanna take over Christopher?
- Yeah, yeah.
So I guess like you were asking about,
like the presentation, right?
Leading up to the presentation.
- [Anu] Oh yeah.
How you came together as you were leading up the,
you have to present your solution
- Definitely. - and you gotta come together.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, between these like, you know, technical building stuff,
we had like some really cool events
like the Duck Hunt event.
The the Duck Hunt event, which is basically where
the Cal Poly DxHub team programmed the chatbot
and they hide like mini ducks around campus
and it has an NFC chip in it
where if you put your phone next to it,
it's gonna pull up a chatbot
and you're supposed to prompt inject it
for the chatbot to give you a clue.
So it's really like awesome. I've never seen-
- Sophisticated treasure. - Exactly.
- Like it was really cool.
'Cause number one, I got my steps in,
Cal Poly is like really big campus.
Number two, I got to like know my team better.
And number three, I got to know,
like the whole like culture of this
because the clues are like designed to like,
designed specifically with like,
hints of Cal Poly culture.
So like they're mentioning like,
oh students hang out here,
so like we get to like experience what, you know,
a four year university is like in a sense.
And you know, that team building
leading up to the presentation
definitely made my team's chemistry much stronger.
And you know, that prepares us for moments where,
even if we're not ready, we have that chemistry say,
oh yeah, you take over this,
I take over that.
You know, like we don't need,
like we don't need to tell them to step up,
they step up,
'cause you know, we have,
we know each other basically.
So that's what should I get at.
- So finish my last thought
and to expand upon what he said,
they really did put so much effort
into like community building.
One of my favorite parts was they had like,
a gumball machine,
but it had little 3D printed trophies
that incentivized like hard work.
And one of my favorite things was like,
identifying someone that was working hard and going up
and recognizing their hard work.
And I made like so many good friends
just from that small action of them,
like feeling recognized.
And then towards the end of the week people were like,
giving me these little trinkets and stuff.
And so I felt, like, that made me wanna work hard.
And when people get recognized for working hard,
that helps them as well.
And so towards the end of the week
there was these different community building engagements
and stuff like that that we did
that really like helped us,
like get through to that finish line
and like give our best each day essentially.
- I think I saw in the Discord
that people were doing like human pyramids on the beach
and like falling off.
- Did you go there
- So basically how it all started was the pizza night.
So how this all started was,
so how the AI camp actually started was a bowling night,
a social like gathering, right?
To get to know each other
and basically like a group of people,
like bundled up in one table
and be like, oh yeah, yeah, yeah,
you go to this college, I go to this college.
You know, like trying to exchange contacts
and stuff like that.
You know, LinkedIn connections.
Then after that we became closer and closer friends,
even though we are in separate teams by the way.
And you know, they went to beaches,
we played Uno at like 12:00 AM
even though we're not supposed to,
we're supposed to be working on our project.
And if I'm not mistaken right now,
we have a group chat
where they're planning to do a skydiving trip, so.
- [Anu] The Discord server was quite active all day,
all night.
- We were doing- - I didn't know
how to turn off my notifications
and I was hearing ding ding, ding, ding,
for a little while, the first two nights.
- If I'm not mistaken, we were doing truth or dares
and like yeah, it the Discord got pretty active.
- The Discord is wild. - Yeah.
So, but we made like really strong connections
through those, like, fun time that's not technical.
- Yeah. - I think for us
as community college leaders,
what I saw in what was happening in the Discord
and in the immersive experiences,
students want community and connection.
And it's often hard when we have students at our campuses
who are, you know, and these were our students,
they're commuter students, they're coming in and out
and what we did is we gave them this
week long immersive experience
where they could be connected, but I don't,
and it's not the end.
They're gonna stay connected.
But it is a lesson in thinking about what are we doing
and how do we continue for our other students
to create that community and that engagement,
and give them a place
because they want it and they're thriving in it.
Sometimes it's weird in the wild, wild west in that Discord,
but you know, but they want it.
And so I think it's another way for us to think about
what are we doing for our students?
How are we creating community?
And giving them these opportunities to build the connections
that I think will help them in their career
and moving forward.
And so, you know,
I appreciate you talking about
that community building aspect.
Was that intentional
when you were all the community building
when you talked about, you know, designing this program?
- 100%. - Yeah. Yeah.
- I mean, that's the major goal. Yeah.
- [Anu] Mentors,
did you also participate in the community building?
And what was community building like for you
and the other group of mentors that you were with?
- I think for us,
like we also went to these social events
and I think even as mentors we really bonded a lot.
Even just like putting the camp together.
Like Christopher mentioned that we had the AI scavenger hunt
that three students from the DxHub team,
they worked on it really hard
and we also had like dry runs
that we did around the campus.
So the whole team, we put like ducks around
just to see like everything is working well.
And I think just that whole process
was also like a really good bonding experience for us.
We had like a much more stronger community after the camp.
And the two weeks together,
we were there from nine to five
and then we had some social events
that we wanted to go to after the whole camp.
And yeah, I think it was like a really good experience
for us too.
- Just real quick,
I think we also made all of our DxHub student mentors
decide who the individual award winners
- Yeah. - were gonna be
and also gauge the actual winning teams and stuff, so.
- [Anu] Because it the work,
can you explain a little bit about the award
after they presented on Friday
and gave their solutions?
- Yeah. - What happened?
- So it wasn't, there's like no money on the line, right?
It was really about - Bragging rights.
- it was bragging rights.
Did your team understand the AI concepts you were applying?
Were you laser focused on customer need
and actually solving that real business problem
among a litany of other things.
And we had individual words which mapped
to the gumball machine
with all the little trinkets in it or whatever.
So like bias for action, a little lightning bolt
or big lightning bolt for whoever won
that one event and simplify.
Some of these are like Amazon leadership principles as well.
The builder trophy, which was a giant Lego person
with a nice bejeweled stash.
It was ultimately a nice touch.
So there were a number of these awards
and then one camper would get the individual awards
and then there was first, second, third
for the teams themselves.
Did we have some awards at this table?
What'd you win?
- I won the AI safety and ethics award
and that was for being-
(audience applauding) Thank you.
I appreciate that.
That was for being considerate
of what the customer was looking for,
as well as how we can safeguard them against loss
and hopefully get them more savings.
- And then you won an award too, right?
- The Invent and Simplify award.
- Invent and simplify. Yeah.
(audience applauding)
Yeah, that's the twisty light bulb, right?
- Yeah, so the award was really cool,
'cause like he could twist it and stuff.
- And then, sorry, I didn't mean to cut you off Sharon.
I think maybe, sorry.
- What, were you gonna say something?
- For the mentor? Yeah.
- [Anu] Oh, for the mentors. Go ahead.
- Yeah. Oh yeah. Okay. I can also speak on that.
I think, yeah, throughout this camp
the mentors definitely got a lot closer,
because usually during regular, like development hours,
we're usually grouped into smaller developer groups
where we don't get the opportunity to really speak with,
like as many developers
because you're just in your group
developing for that project.
But through the summer camp,
we were able to talk to everyone more
and discuss like different approaches
and like to the different solutions
and it was a great way to, yeah, collaborate
just through the mentors themselves as well.
- So I know we talked about all the great things
and the positive things.
It wasn't all perfect, right, Christopher and River.
And can you tell me what some of the challenges were
or that you either experienced
or Nick or Ryan that you observed?
- I'll go first. - 'Cause those
are life changing too.
- I don't think anything was like,
pull your hair out, stressful, challenging.
I think all the challenges were like constructive.
There were moments in time where I was like,
am I gonna be able to submit a project
that is worth anything?
Like am I wasting everyone's time
by telling them to do all these things?
So there's a lot of second guessing myself
and kind of like imposter syndrome as far as like,
wow, everyone around here is so talented
and so good at what they do.
Like am I really one of these kids as well?
And so I think getting over that
was one of the challenges for me.
And the way that I got through that,
was just like those community building engagements
when I started interacting with like the mentors
or like the faculty,
or like the fellow students,
I did really felt like I belonged there.
And towards the end of it I was like thinking like,
wow, everyone really did get selected, like for a reason.
'Cause I tried to talk to everyone at the camp,
like I'm kind of antisocial,
so I pushed myself to be more social
and so I'm walking around talking to everyone
and each person had just such a unique, interesting story.
I'm sure they all have their own unique challenges,
but we did like come together
to like overcome those challenges.
So I think that was really cool.
- Yeah, yeah. I definitely agree with that.
And also I guess a more technical challenge for,
well, I think for most of the teams are like,
I feel like the data
that the California Community College system has is really,
I mean the data is there, right?
I think building systems around these data
could be difficult
because, you know, it's not like smooth Lego bricks
that connect with each other, right?
Like the data could be all sorts
of different sizes and shapes.
So I guess a technical challenge was,
building a system that's compatible with an MVP,
but then having that mindset that, you know,
this could potentially scale
and the data could get even more messier
and more complicated.
And I guess that's also like generally how AI works.
Like it's really challenging to work with
data that's garbage, right?
So garbage in, garbage out.
If it's not good,
then it's probably not gonna be good in production.
- Christopher, you learned in one week a lesson
that all of us in system have experience,
which is we have incompatible systems often
in our institutions, across our institutions,
across our district, so. - I agree.
- Good luck. (laughs) I agree.
Yes, they did experience that.
- Just on the first off, you know,
thank you all for like dealing with
last minute agenda changes
or a lack of data or specificity.
Ryan kind of alluded to,
we don't expect that we know the answer
or the right solution
and that's a part of the process.
We did like, I don't know,
15 discovery sessions in two weeks leading up to the camp,
this recording, you know, the pain points,
basically interviewing the business experts,
like what are your pain points?
What are the data sets that we could get access to?
What would really good look like? Right?
And then all that got packaged up and passed in
and some teams didn't have as much as other teams.
There were some teams that literally had to create
synthetic data out of nowhere and go,
lots of teams were scraping data off the web.
So thank you for like embracing that ambiguity
and just kind of rolling with it.
I think one of my biggest observations was,
I think we lost two teams.
It's the community college, right?
- We had to adjust significantly.
- Yeah, so we team rebalancing.
It's almost like a little mini HR function
would have like a well thought out one
would've been incredibly easy.
We we did it on offline
and I think we did it more or less successfully,
but like team dynamics and participation
and just like the chemistry
and stuff, some teams really clearly clicked
and some teams totally struggled
and we had to kind of lean in
and figure that out a little bit.
And by the way, I feel like I heard from all the mentors
that they also kind of had imposter syndrome
at the same time.
So I think that's kind of interesting.
- Yeah, yeah. And it's a summer camp
and it was intensive by design.
And so we tried to communicate consistently every hour
like, we are here to support you.
Let us know what you need. And they did.
And we got calls at two in the morning
and we got to go to Costco and buy towels
because there weren't enough.
And like that part of the experience was amazing to me.
I mean, Nick and I are both fathers,
we both have daughters
that someday will be community college
or CSU or other students.
But the mentors really stepped up and like,
it was such a great supportive environment
and that that was our hope,
that was our dream.
We did everything we could to craft that.
But pretty much just standing back
and watching you all step into that, you were naturals.
I mean, I was so amazed.
I wanna give our mentors around applause.
(all applauding)
- I wanna give all of you a round of applause
because what you've put together,
(audience applauding)
what you put together really is what we're trying to do
as you know, when Chancellor Christian
and all of our presidents
and chancellors talk about how are we preparing students,
how are we getting them workforce ready?
How are we helping them find purpose-driven career
and personal outcomes?
How are we helping them reach that?
And so this really,
this experience I think set out to do that
and we're hoping to be able to replicate and scale.
And then as we kind of close us out,
we have a highlight video that we just wanna show you,
so you get to see all the things they talked about
and what it was like to be in that room that week.
(upbeat music)
- [Student] Hartnell College is our client.
If we were challenged to develop
an AI power career exploration tool
that helps undecided community college students
discover appropriate majors.
- [Student] We created Allen Live Access named the after
De Anza and Foothills, which is our customer.
- [Alex] Hi there,
this is Alex from the Allen Live Disability Services
tutoring center from
the De Anza and Foothill College District.
I'm here to help you schedule a tutoring appointment
that's perfectly tailored to your needs.
May I start by getting your name?
- [Christopher] Yeah, my name is Christopher.
- [Alex] Thank you so much Christopher,
it's great to meet you.
I'll make sure we get you the.
Great to meet you Christopher.
Now I'll be your student ID number,
so I can access your profile.
- [Christopher] So let's try and do it on AI.
- What's your student ID? - Do I really have
to give you my student ID?
- [Alex] That's a great question Christopher
and I completely understand your hesitation.
We ask for your student ID
just to make sure we're looking at the right profile
and can provide you with the best support possible.
Your information is always kept private
and only used to help you get the services you need.
If you're comfortable,
could you please share your student ID with me?
- [Christopher] All right, I gotta go
because there's no more time.
(audience applauding)
We are trying to support small businesses in California.
- [Student] So yeah, this is our main dashboard.
- [Student] In addition to our chatbot,
we produce a demo with Amazon's new Nova Sonic model.
- [Student] I want SAT score,
do I need to be eligible for calculus?
- [Alex] Hey there.
To be eligible for calculus at Cal Poly,
you need an SAT math score of 620 or above.
Alternatively, you can also call-
- [Student] All right, that's enough information.
Thank you. - You're welcome.
(audience applauding)
- [Student] Can that matching feature,
I think that's really cool.
and that also help on the other end in terms of like,
those who are going to be reading
and awarding scholarships.
Do you see that as kind of a connection?
- [Student] Definitely, yeah.
That could definitely be implemented in the backwards
or the foundation themselves of working in.
- [Student] And what you wanna make sure is that the money
and the tuition that you are putting into university
is being used practically
and is not being spent carelessly honestly without,
you know, consideration for what it's going into.
- [Student] Well said.
And that's what we're trying to target the students
who need that additional support
to figure out their career paths, majors,
and any potential certificate they'd like to pursue.
We'd also like to target the academic advisors
and counselors at Centers Junior College.
- [Student] Two big changes,
required trainings have right there
and the training assistant right there.
- [Student] So the experience is just made for
the experience to be more tailored to the learning.
- [Student] We are lucky,
if you take anything from PDF forms
to training manuals, to payroll schedules,
and explains the information
that you are looking for in a concise
and easy to understand conversational manner.
- [Student] Debate over who gets prizes.
(audience laughing)
- Intense debate. - Award goes to River.
(audience applauding) (audience cheering)
- River. (audience laughing)
(audience applauding)
- Thank you to all of you for joining us today.
Thank you again, panelists.
As you can see, we really try to give an experience here
through this partnership
for how we can train our and be make workforce ready,
for students for tomorrow if there's any questions?
Yeah, we're, go ahead.
- [Audience member] I'd love to ask
just real quick question. - Sure.
- [Audience member] Students and the mentors,
knowing what you know now and having had experiences,
is there one gnarly challenge
that you wanna tackle or you want someone to tackle with AI?
- I really want to be able to communicate
with Canvas in like a better way.
I think that workflow could be improved.
I'm actually doing a hackathon where I'm trying to integrate
Google Gemini Notion and Canvas.
So you could essentially just talk to Google Gemini
and have it tell you your Canvas solution.
So I think stuff that can help students succeed academically
would have like a two-pronged approach,
'cause it would have such a positive impact
on students in the future.
But then building those tools
are a challenge within themselves.
- I really wanna mention,
if there's one thing that I want community colleges,
the California Community College system to focus on is,
standardizing the data.
(audience laughing)
- You'll have to come work for us in the future.
- Yeah.
- I spent, like, days looking at like data
that's like, not like, it's like really outdated
and it's really hard to deal with, you know,
like, you know the CID super numbering system assist,
how it's not compatible.
How it's not compatible with CVC,
that's another SaaS.
It's like really hard to connect these.
Like the data is there, right?
But it's so disconnected and disjointed that, you know,
why not standardize this?
- Yes. - Yes. (laughs)
(audience applauding)
And you had a question back there.
- [Audience member] Oh yeah.
For the students in emerging protocol frameworks,
do you see your self in (speaking softly)
as technical as you want.
- I'm attending an event tomorrow
with the host is Dom Sagolla,
he was one of the early Twitter members
and he's developing a platform called Gray Whale AI.
And I think that should be really interesting.
I don't know too much about it,
'cause it's proprietary,
but essentially he's saying it's gonna use
a thousand times less data
and Bill Tai is a venture capitalist
who is funding the event
and there's some pretty impressive sponsors and stuff.
So I think keeping an eye on that space
and a agentic AI,
just that entire realm is probably where like the AI feature
is going, in my opinion.
- One thing that I would
like to see is definitely MCP servers.
It's really popular.
It's taking the LLM agentic AI scene by storm.
It's became like the, the standard and the norm.
And I feel like all these educational focused SaaS,
like Ellucian, Canvas, Instructure, Cengage,
should all adapt MCP as a standard
so that, you know, LLM tools
that could be built by the future,
CC AI camp students
wouldn't have to go through documents of AI pages,
but just give this, you know, MCP server documentation
to an LLM and it's gonna be integrated with context
engineering built into it, right?
So I guess that's one thing I wanna see.
- Okay. Thank you very much for joining us.
(audience applauding)
Lunch is next
and it's going to be in the exhibit hall,
in the Futurist Hub, so, and then there's.